Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551 10 Center Dr Bethesda, MD 20892

■ simon.liu@nih.gov - 🗷 nhgri/medical.genetics.branch

■ simon@simonliu.dev - 🚱 simonliu.dev

github/simonliu99 - porcid/0000-0002-1182-5492

🛅 linkedin/simonliu99 - 🗏 google.scholar

Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate IRTA fellow in the Medical Genomics Unit at the X National Human Genome Research Institute, interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to genetics datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators.

Education

Bachelor of Science, Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD. 08/2017 - 05/2021

Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science Linda Trinh Memorial Award, Joseph F. Strohecker Scholarship Honors: Unsilon Pi Ensilon Dean's list general & RMF+CS depart

Honors: Upsilon Pi Epsilon, Dean's list, general & BME+CS departmental honors

GPA: 3.69

Research Experience

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present With Benjamin Solomon

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, 02/2020 - 05/2021

Baltimore, MD, USA.

With Chad Gordon.
Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [award] [news]

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 12/2018 - 03/2020

With Susan Hutfless

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, 07/2018 - 03/2020

USA

With Junfang Wu

Volunteer Experience

Care Coordinator, Pan Asian Volunteer Health Clinic, Chinese Culture and Community Service 10/2021 - present Center, Gaithersburg, MD.

With Mo-Ping Chow and Yaoyao Zhu

Teaching Experience

Course Assistant, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, 08/2020 - 05/2021 USA.

With Kwame Kutten

Publications

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Web of Science.

Journal Articles

Liu, Y., Chen, S., **Liu, S.**, Wallace, K. L., Zille, M., Zhang, J., Wang, J., & Jiang, C. (2023). T-cell receptor signaling modulated by the co-receptors: Potential targets for stroke treatment. Pharmacological Research, 192, 106797. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2023.106797 [pdf]

J-9

1-8

Zhang, Z., Li, Y., Shi, J., Zhu, L., Dai, Y., Fu, P., **Liu, S.**, Hong, M., Zhang, J., Wang, J., & Jiang, C. (2022). Lymphocyte-related immunomodulatory therapy with Siponimod (BAF-312) improves outcomes in mice with acute intracerebral hemorrhage. Aging and Disease.

https://doi.org/10.14336/ad.2022.1102 [pdf]

Jiang, C., Guo, H., Zhang, Z., Wang, Y., **Liu, S.**, Lai, J., Wang, T. J., Li, S., Zhang, J., Zhu, L., Fu, P., Zhang, J., & Wang, J. (2022). Molecular, pathological, clinical, and therapeutic aspects of perihematomal edema in different stages of intracerebral hemorrhage. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2022, 1–38. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/3948921 [pdf]

	Hutfless, S., Shiratori, Y., Chu, D., Liu, S. , & Kalloo, A. (2022). Risk factors for infections after endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP): A retrospective cohort analysis of US Medicare Fee-for-Service claims, 2015–2021. BMJ Open, 12(9). https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-065077 [pdf]	J-7	
	Sun, C., Han, Y., Zhang, R., Liu, S. , Wang, J., Zhang, Y., Chen, X., Jiang, C., Wang, J., Fan, X., & Wang, J. (2022). Regulated necrosis in COVID-19: A double-edged sword. Frontiers in Immunology, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.917141 [pdf]	J-6	
	Hutfless, S., Jasper, R. A., Tilak, A., Ghosh, T., Kedia, S., Liu, S. , Urrunaga, N. H., Josephson, M., Narang, A., Miller, S., Chen, PH., Joseph, S., & Brant, S. R. (2022). A systematic review of Crohn's disease case definitions in administrative or claims databases. Inflammatory Bowel Diseases. https://doi.org/10.1093/ibd/izac131 [pdf]	J-5	
	Ledgister Hanchard, S. E.*, Dwyer, M. C.*, Liu, S. *, Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R. L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B. D. (2022). Scoping review and classification of Deep Learning in Medical Genetics. Genetics in Medicine. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gim.2022.04.025 *Co-first authors. [pdf]	J-4	
	Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. E., Liu, S. , Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2022). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes. Frontiers in Genetics, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.864092 [pdf]	J-3	
	Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., Liu, S. , Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltage-gated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267–283. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005 [pdf]	J-2	
	Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., Liu, S. , Li, H., Stoica, B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376–11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199 [pdf]	J-1	
Conference Papers	Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., Liu, S. , Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-guided colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging 2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020). https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873 [pdf]	C-1	
Meeting Abstracts	Patel, R., Palamuttam, N., Choi, Y., Diamreyan, M., Liu, S. , Park, S.J., Salazar, S., & Goeddel, L. (2021). Intraoperative hypotension before critical care admission is common but not associated with in hospital mortality in non-cardiac surgery. Anesthesia & Analgesia, 132(5S):859-862. https://doi.org/10.1213/01.ane.0000803544.47940.c7 [pdf]	A-3	
	Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., Liu, S. , & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314 [pdf]	A-2	
	Hutfless, S. M., Chen, PH., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., Liu, S. , Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology, 158(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/s0016-5085(20)31712-1 [pdf]	A-1	
Presentations	Liu, S. , Ledgister Hanchard, S., Dwyer, M.C., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Applications of deep learning in medical genetics. Poster presented at: NIH Virtual Postbac Poster Day 2022; Bethesda, MD. [poster] [pdf]	P-1	
Selected Honors	Outstanding Volunteer Award, Chinese Culture and Community Service Center, Gaithersburg, MD, USA	11/2022	
	Awarded at the Chinese Culture and Community Service Center 40th Anniversary Celebration [award] [yearbook]		
	Linda Trinh Memorial Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA	05/2021	
	Project: COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shiel With Y. Bai, J. Feitelberg, K. Hu, S. Kumar, K. Leo, J. Li, C. Shallal, and N. Zhang	ds [blog] [news]	
	Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up, Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray. [report] [ppt] [award]	12/2020	
	With F. Shao, Y. Huang, and A. Harmalkar.		
	Provost's Undergraduate Research Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	11/2020	
	Projects Implementing Electronic Peam Steering in an Implantable Ultracound Device Jaward Inquel		

Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device [award] [news]

With Chad Gordon.

	Upsilon Pi Epsilon , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. International Honor Society for the Computing and Information Disciplines	10/2020
	Joseph F. Strohecker Scholarship, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.	11/2017 06/2017
Selected Press	Liu, Simon. "Making an Impact Outside of the Laboratory" Office of Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion, National Institutes of Health. May 1, 2023.	2023
	Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input Mag. February 18, 2022.	2022
	Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019.	2019
	Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News- Letter. November 15, 2018.	2018

Selected Coursework

Computer Integrated Surgery I Computer Integrated Surgery II Machine Learning Machine Learning: Deep Learning Biomedical Data Science Precision Care Medicine I Precision Care Medicine II

Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

Extracurricular Experience

Vice President of Finance, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA	11/2019 - 12/2020
Pledge Educator, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA	05/2019 - 11/2019
Head of Manufacturing, Health 3D, LLC, Baltimore, MD, USA.	04/2018 - 05/2021

Metadata

This document lives online at https://simonliu.dev/cv/.

A downloadable version can be found at https://simonliu.dev/files/liu_cv.pdf.

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp. MIT License.

Last updated: May 25, 2023